Guide to the Veronica Melendez photographs, 2011-2012 RL.11692
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Veronica Melendez photographs
2011-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Melendez, Veronica Aracely
RL.11692
1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 20 color inkjet prints 17 x 22 inches
Twenty 17x22-inch color inkjet prints from the body of work "Le pido a Dios que no me olviden," or "I ask God that you not forget me," by photographer Veronica Melendez document the Latin American community in the Washington, D.C. metro area, primarily in Maryland and Virginia. The images are of people, cultural events, religious scenes, and symbols that recall faraway countries of origin as well as contemporary realities in these Latin American communities. Melendez's work received the 2018 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of the American South. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged in original order as assigned by the photographer.
Biographical Note
Veronica Melendez is a visual artist currently based in Washington, D.C. She received her MFA from the University of Hartford and BFA from the Corcoran College of Art and Design. From illustrations of iconic household products to photographs documenting the diaspora of Central Americans within the D.C. metro area, her work is greatly influenced by her Latinx upbringing. Melendez is the 2018 recipient of the Duke University Archive of Documentary Arts Collection Award for Documentarians of the American South.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Provenance
The Veronica Melendez photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The inkjet photographs in this collection were printed using Epson Ultra Premium Photo Paper Luster.
Content Description
The title of this project, Le pido a Dios que no me olviden, translates to "I ask God that you not forget me." It is taken from a letter written to the artist's mother the day she emigrated from Guatemala to the United States in 1982. These words inspired Veronica Melendez to start documenting through photography the Central American community in the Washington, D.C. metro area, particularly in Maryland and Virginia.
The twenty 17x22-inch color inkjet prints, all horizontally oriented, document people, cultural events, religious scenes, and symbols that recall faraway countries of origin as well as contemporary realities in these Latin American communities. The artist's statement is included. This work won the 2018 ADA Collection Award for Documentarians of the American South.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Documentary photography -- Washington (D.C.); Immigrants -- Southern States -- Photographs; Latin Americans -- Photographs; Latin Americans -- United States; Latin Americans -- United States -- Social conditions; Latin Americans -- Washington (D.C.); Maryland -- Photographs; Virginia, Northern -- Photographs; Washington (D.C.) -- Photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Melendez, Veronica Aracely
- Le pido a Dios que no me olviden, 2011-2012; All prints measure 17x22 inches and are horizontally oriented.
  - Casa furniture, Alexandria, Virginia, 2011; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0001)
  - Abuela en navidad, Wheaton, Maryland, 2011; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0002)
  - John Rios en casa, Wheaton, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0003)
  - Graduation party, Potomac, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0004)
  - Latino laundry, Falls Church, Virginia, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0005)
  - Checkers, Wheaton, Maryland, 2011; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0006)
  - Niños jugando, Langley Park, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0007)
  - Shadows, Langley Park, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0008)
  - Hechizo, Alexandria, Virginia, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0009)
  - Iglesia De Cristo, Glenmont, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0010)
  - Juan, Layhill Road, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0011)
  - Primas, Wheaton, Maryland, 2011; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0012)
  - Comedor, Wheaton, Maryland, 2011; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0013)
  - Abuelo de John, Wheaton, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0014)
  - Bible boy, Glenmont, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0015)
  - Western Jesus, Glenmont, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0016)
  - Mama Olivia en casa, Silver Spring, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0017)
  - John 17:18, Glenmont, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0018)
  - La Mount Pleasant, Mount Pleasant, Washington D.C, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0019)
  - Andrea en casa, Wheaton, Maryland, 2012; 17 x 22 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11692-P-0020)